<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section>
    <title>The YaST2 Macro Recorder</title>

    <simpara>
        Target Audience:
    </simpara>

    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <simpara>
                YaST2 power users
            </simpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <simpara>
                Quality assurance (Testers)
            </simpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <simpara>
                Technical writers
            </simpara>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <section>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <simpara>
            The YaST2 UI (User Interface) features a macro recorder and player that records
            user interaction during installation or system configuration and plays those
            user actions at a later time in the same scenario.
        </simpara>

        <simpara>
            The Qt (graphical) and NCurses (text mode) user interfaces both support the
            macro recorder. It is also independent of graphics mode, display resolution,
            widget theme, terminal type or other details of the desktop being used: Not
            low-level input device (mouse or keyboard) events are recorded but logical user
            actions such as "Accept button was activated", and widget status information is
            saved in terms as "the <emphasis>user name</emphasis> input field contains <emphasis>tux</emphasis>", not individual
            keystrokes that might include lots of cursor movement and hitting the
            "backspace" key.
        </simpara>

        <simpara>
            Macros recorded in one environment using the Qt UI may be played in another
            using the NCurses UI - unless, of course, the dialogs in either situation have
            completely different contents because extended features were used the other UI
            is not capable of. This should occur only very rarely, however.
        </simpara>

    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Quick Start</title>
        <simpara>
            Since most readers are impatient and just want to know how to get it going,
            here is a quick start guide - but PLEASE read the other sections anyway to
            avoid disappointment or even severe data loss:
        </simpara>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <simpara>
                    Start a YaST2 module in Qt (grahpical) mode - from the YaST2 control center,
                    from the KDE control center, from the desktop menu or via command line.
                </simpara>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <simpara>
                    To record a macro, press <keycap>Alt-Ctrl-Shift M</keycap>
                    The sequence of first Alt, then Ctrl, then Shift is important!
                    A file selection box opens prompting you to enter a file name for the macro.
                    Make sure you have write permission to the directory you select.
                </simpara>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <simpara>
                    Work with the YaST2 module as usual.
                </simpara>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <simpara>
                    Press <keycap>Alt-Ctrl-Shift M</keycap> again to stop recording. When the module is finished
                    of course recording stops automatically.
                </simpara>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <simpara>
                    Start the same module again.
                </simpara>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <simpara>
                    To play a macro, press <keycap>Alt-Ctrl-Shift P</keycap>.
                </simpara>
                <simpara>
                    A file selection box opens. Select the macro file you recorded
                    earlier.
                </simpara>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <simpara>
                    Watch the YaST2 module replay the same you did when recording the macro.
                </simpara>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <simpara>
            Alternatively, you can also supply a macro on the
            <command>"y2base"</command> command line:
        </simpara>

        <screen>
            /usr/lib/YaST2/bin/y2base some_yast2_module qt --macro /wherever/macro.ycp
        </screen>
        <screen>
            /usr/lib/YaST2/bin/y2base some_yast2_module ncurses --macro /wherever/macro.ycp
        </screen>
        <simpara>
            This is currently the only way to play macros with the NCurses (text mode) UI -
            it doesn't provide special key combinations for recording or playing macros
            (yet).
        </simpara>

    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Purpose</title>
        <simpara>
            The general idea of this macro recorder is to provide an easy way of automating
            repetetive tasks on the user level - for automated testing and to easily
            produce lots of screen shots in recurring situations.
        </simpara>

        <simpara>
            For example, the SuSE Linux installation manuals include lots of screen shots
            that of course look differently in each language, and it is very desirable to
            have the screen shot in the same language as the rest of the manual. For the
            documentation department, this means that all required screen shots have to be
            made in all languages we ship translated manuals for, so all relevant
            installation scenarios have to be restaged with only the language being
            different. To make matters worse, the responsible person might not even
            understand all those languages and thus has to rely on guessing what button to
            click on.
        </simpara>

        <simpara>
            With the macro recorder, he can record a macro in a language he understands, do
            all screen shots there, then restart the process, select another language and
            play the macro - all screen shots he took will then automatically be made in
            that language. Of course, not a button text like "Accept" is being recorded,
            but an internal logical button name that doesn't change depending on language.
        </simpara>

    </section>
    <section>
        <title>What it is not</title>
        <simpara>
            The macro recorder is not intended as a poor man's substitute for AutoYaST, the
            automatic untattended installation - even though it can be (mis-) used that way
            to some degree.
        </simpara>

        <simpara>
            If you have lots of machines to install in a similar way, use AutoYaST, not the
            macro recorder: The macro recorder is dumb. It will blindly repeat whatever you
            did while recording the macro. If however at some other machine the situation
            is only slightly different, this might easily not work any more: If there are
            hard disks of different size or with a different partitioning scheme and you
            didn't rely on YaST2's automatic modes but created partitions manually, this
            might fail on the other machine.
        </simpara>

        <simpara>
            Then you will get an error dialog, at which point your macro will no longer
            match the situation, but of course the macro will not realize this and happily
            keep playing user actions that are completely out of sync with the dialogs
            on-screen. Usually this will just cause lots of more error dialogs, but chances
            are that it might keep working for a while and cause data loss on that machine.
        </simpara>

        <simpara>
            Note: This might even happen at the same machine if the environment just
            changed a bit - if, say, you added a hard disk partition in the first run, this
            might fail in the second run (or in the third or fourth run) because there is
            no more free space on the disk. Then you will also get error dialogs.
        </simpara>

        <simpara>
            AutoYaST on the other hand takes all this into account and reacts in a much
            more intelligent way.
        </simpara>

    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Quirks and Limitations</title>
        <simpara>
            Given the intentions and target user group of the macro recorder, there are
            some known limitations that will very likely remain for the forseeable future:
        </simpara>

        <simpara>
            Some widgets in the Qt UI "eat" the special key combinations. If one of those
            has the keyboard focus, pressing Alt-Ctrl-Shift M (or P) will have no effect.
            But there is an easy workaround: Simply move the keyboard focus with the
            "Tab" key to another widget like a push button - this will not change the
            environment for macro recording or playing. It is otherwise irrelevant to the
            macro recorder which widget has the keyboard focus.
        </simpara>
        <simpara>
            Qt selection boxes are particular notable for this - you have to hit "Tab" in
            the language selection in the first dialog of a YaST2 installation before you
            can start recording or playing a macro there.
        </simpara>
        <simpara>
            The software package manager user interface does not support the macro
            recorder at all. This was the tradeoff for getting a user interface that
            powerful: All that dialog is one large widget written purely in C++ unlike
            almost all other YaST2 dialogs.
        </simpara>
        <simpara>
            If you use the macro recorder, don't go into the detailed software selection.
        </simpara>
        <simpara>
            The Qt version of the YaST2 control center also does not support the macro
            recorder at all. It is a relatively basic Qt/C++ program that acts as a
            program launcher for the YaST2 modules, but it is not connected to them very
            closely. This was also a tradeoff: It is optimized for pretty looks and fast
            startup time.
        </simpara>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Anatomy of a Macro</title>
        <simpara>
            Here is an example of a macro recorded during the first part of a YaST2
            installation:
        </simpara>

        <simpara>
            In the language dialog, "German" was selected.  Notice how there are no German
            texts to be seen anywhere inside the macro - only symbolic names are used.
        </simpara>

        <simpara>
            Then in a popup asking whether to update or to do a new installation
            "installation" was chosen.
        </simpara>

        <simpara>
            From the installation settings proposal "software" was selected to change the
            amount of software to install from "default system" to "minimal+X11".
        </simpara>

        <simpara>
            Then the installation was started.
        </simpara>

        <example>
            <title>YaST2 UI macro file</title>
            <programlisting>
// YaST2 UI macro file generated by UI macro recorder
//
//     Qt UI: Alt-Ctrl-Shift-M: start/stop Macro recorder
//            Alt-Ctrl-Shift-P: Play macro
//
// Each block will be executed just before the next UserInput().
// 'return' before the closing brace ( '}' ) of each block relinquishes control
// back to the YCP source.
// Inside each block arbitrary YCP code can be added manually.

{
    {
        UI::ChangeWidget( `id (`language),	`CurrentItem,	"de_DE" );	// YSelectionBox

        // UI::MakeScreenShot( "/tmp/yast2-0000" );
        UI::FakeUserInput( `language );

        return;
    }

    {
        UI::ChangeWidget( `id (`language),	`CurrentItem,	"de_DE" );	// YSelectionBox

        UI::MakeScreenShot( "/tmp/screen-shots/language-selection.png" );
        // UI::MakeScreenShot( "/tmp/yast2-0001" );
        UI::FakeUserInput( `accept );

        return;
    }

    {
        UI::ChangeWidget( `id (`install),	`Value,	true );	// YRadioButton

        // UI::MakeScreenShot( "/tmp/yast2-0002" );
        UI::FakeUserInput( `ok );

        return;
    }

    {
        // UI::MakeScreenShot( "/tmp/yast2-0003" );
        UI::FakeUserInput( "software" );

        return;
    }

    {
        UI::ChangeWidget( `id ("Minimal+X11"),	`Value,	true );	// YRadioButton

        UI::MakeScreenShot( "/tmp/screen-shots/sw-base-selection.png" );
        // UI::MakeScreenShot( "/tmp/yast2-0004" );
        UI::FakeUserInput( "Minimal+X11" );

        return;
    }

    {
        UI::ChangeWidget( `id ("Minimal+X11"),	`Value,	true );	// YRadioButton

        // UI::MakeScreenShot( "/tmp/yast2-0005" );
        UI::FakeUserInput( `accept );

        return;
    }

    {
        // UI::MakeScreenShot( "/tmp/yast2-0006" );
        UI::FakeUserInput( `accept );

        return;
    }

}
</programlisting>
</example>

<simpara>
    Each dialog that is opened gets its own block enclosed in curly braces
    ( "{..}" ). In each block, the status of each widget that holds status
    information is restored (UI::ChangeWidget()).
</simpara>

<simpara>
    Then there is a chance to make a screen shot; the macro recorder automatically
    adds a UI::MakeScreenShot() statement at the appropriate place, assigning
    generic file names that end in numbers. This statement is commented out by
    default as indicated by leading double slashes ( "//" ) - this makes it simple
    to enable it if desired.
</simpara>

<simpara>
    If the user explicitly hits the [PrintScreen] key to make a screen shot,
    another UI::MakeScreenShot() call (this time not commented out) will be added
    with the exact file name the user entered at the file selection box. The idea
    is to give the user a chance to assign more descriptive names to the screen
    shots.
</simpara>

<simpara>
    After that, UI::FakeUserInput() simulates the same input the user had done
    while recording the macro. Usually, this is activation of a push button (like
    `accept as seen so many times above), but it can also be changing a selection
    box like in the language selection at the start of the macro (for insiders: if
    the widget has `opt(`notify) set).
</simpara>

<simpara>
    The last line is a "return" statement that returns control flow from the macro
    block to the application that is being executed.
</simpara>

<simpara>
    When the next dialog is executed (for insiders: when UI::UserInput() or related
    are called), the next macro block is executed.
</simpara>

<simpara>
    So not only is the mechanism very generic, the code that is produced is also
    plain YCP code that is readable and that can easily be adapted if necessary.
</simpara>

</section>
</section>
